<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Androidgrl's Blog</title>
 <link href="http://androidgrl.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://androidgrl.github.io/"/>
 <updated>2015-08-28T17:29:52-06:00</updated>
 <id>http://androidgrl.github.io</id>
 <author>
   <name>Jamie Kawahara</name>
   <email>kawaharajamie@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>How to add custom text to a 3D model</title>
   <link href="http://androidgrl.github.io/2015/08/07/text/"/>
   <updated>2015-08-07T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://androidgrl.github.io/2015/08/07/text</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a tutorial on how to add custom text to a 3D model, using Tinkercad’s free easy-to-use web-based 3D modeling tool.  This is great for adding personal messages and names to your prints!  In this tutorial I will add custom text to a trophy downloaded from Thingiverse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;./public/trophy.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image of Trophy with Printed Text&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Pictured here is a trophy with custom text added&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since it is much easier to demonstrate how to do this with a video, I have made a short
7 minute &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Youtube video&lt;/a&gt; which demonstrates:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How to download the file from Thingiverse.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How to remove the pre-existing text from the model using Tinkercad.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How to add your own custom text.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to use a Kinect to take a 3D scan and Print It</title>
   <link href="http://androidgrl.github.io/2015/07/30/kinect/"/>
   <updated>2015-07-30T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://androidgrl.github.io/2015/07/30/kinect</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a tutorial on how to use a Kinect to take a 3D scan and print it on a Lulzbot printer.
Follow these instructions and you will be able to make a 3D print of a person!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;./public/rick.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image of 3D print of Rick Bacci&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Pictured here is a model of my friend Rick Bacci&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Download Skanect free software from &lt;a href=&quot;http://skanect.occipital.com/&quot;&gt;Skanect Occipital&lt;/a&gt; note this free version will only allow you to save a low resolution of your scan.  For high resolution you will have to buy the software (cost $130).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Plug in the Kinect to your computer before opening the Skanect software&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Open Skanect&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Watch my &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8Nm2ufFYNBI&quot;&gt;Youtube video&lt;/a&gt; which demonstrates: how to make a scan of a person, how to export it as an .stl file, and how to import the file to slic3r.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once it’s imported to slic3r, follow the instructions below for how to make a print on a lulzbot Taz 4.  Or, proceed with your usual way of making 3D prints! &lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/0361b0f2b917a1c322f3.js&quot;&gt; &lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
